welcome to meditating genre making we do
this every weekday morning at 9 30 am
eastern time with mondays alternating
between a news
lesson dharma day and a review of the
entire ecology practices called upio day
a couple of announcements about this
next monday
which i believe is august the 3rd is a
holiday in canada
so we won't be meeting what's going to
happen to the
scheduled dharma day is it will move to
the following monday
so we will start the wisdom of hypatia
and the western wisdom tradition wisdom
cultivation tradition
on august the 10th i believe it is
that's the following monday
but one thing i will do next week is
next wednesday
i will add in the arms to the tai chi
walking to make more full body
and then you will be actually doing what
are called brush needs
so we will do that next wednesday
okay uh i think that's it in terms of
timing issues i would encourage people
to meet on the discord server
on monday in order to continue their
meditation practice if you're joining us
for the first time
you're most welcome i recommend going to
the description for this video where
you'll find links to previous lessons
and sets
do lesson one immediately keep meeting
with us try to do one or two lessons a
week
and eventually uh you will catch up to
us and
that way you'll have the benefit of the
sangha uh right away
i would ask you all please help me to
help as many people as possible
by liking this stream to increase its
visibility in the youtube algorithm
at the end of every session uh we have a
q a please limit your questions
uh to at that time please limit your
questions
to anything from this entire ecology of
practice
for more general questions and some of
the questions that you guys bring up in
the chat get slot over into the general
q a there is a general q a live streamed
on youtube every third friday
of the month at 3 p.m eastern time
so i think that's it i think we're all
caught up um
i hope everybody is
what's the right what did i what would
be a very helpful
i hope everybody is finding the path
that we're on together
enriching and edifying um not
necessarily easy
but challenging in a way that is
nevertheless
um educational that is drawing something
out from them
and for them so let's get into position
let's set your phones and do not disturb
we will as always now begin with
chanting
we will go into a silent set and then we
will practice coming out of the sitcom
because how you come out of this is as
important
as what's happening in the set uh by
perhaps reciting the five promises
silently to yourself
if you're new um when just take a
general attitude of
about when you're coming out of the
practice to try and slowly integrate
what you've cultivated in your practice
with your everyday consciousness and
cognition
your sense of your character communitas
which is your sense of
how you participate and with
in groups especially perhaps in the
senate
and just set your intention uh to try
and lead
a more mindful and present life
okay we will begin when i say it again
begin
[Music]
um
home
[Music]
um
on
one
[Music]
begin your silencer
so
so they come out of your practice trying
as best you can to integrate
but you cultivated any practice with
your everyday consciousness cognition
character communication perhaps by
reciting
the five promises to yourself
all right so uh we'll take some
questions
hopefully there are some questions just
wait for them to come up on the screen
please be patient everyone we're just
trying to get some
here we go um here's a question from
manual post
i've been gradually getting my back
getting back my ability to visualize
things at least passively
i'm a little bit worried because that
because my unfamiliar with that
experience
it will overwhelm me
um so
manuel i'm trying to figure out what the
issue is here
you lost your ability to visualize
things you mean in mental imagery
um or do you mean in some sort of sense
of anticipation of the future
um and if you're unfamiliar with that
experience it will overwhelm me like
it's coming back
we're talking about something like a
hypnagogic energy or something like an
active
imagination manual if you're watching um
it would help be if you uh there's
various
things you could be meaning there and
i'm not clear and there's too many
options to try and all answer them i
think it would get confusing
if you could please re-ask your question
um
on tuesday or wednesday next week
[Music]
and maybe break it down in a series of
related questions
because i have a sense that something
important is happening here and we do
need to talk more about the imagination
within this whole process
the imagination will figure much more
prominently
in the western wisdom practice
visualization
techniques and practices um but i'm not
quite sure how to
answer you emanuel so if you could
please give me
um more specific maybe two or three
questions that more specifically
explicate
what you're trying to ask me i'd like to
give you my best possible answer
um glenn barnett do you have any sense
to the idea of
gospel patrons and supporting uh the
artists um i
i i'm not sure about that um i need to
talk uh to amar and
uh to jason uh because i'm largely
ignorant
of about what a gospel patron is and
what how we might make that work or how
we might support some of the artists
um in the sangha in
a fair and appropriate manner um i don't
know glenn
um that's again sorry she seems like i'm
doing when i was postponing
i i need to have a more in-depth
discussion uh with ammar
about um all of this
any thoughts on meditating with japanese
music
this is also from glen um
so glenn it's a good idea um
there's a there's a there's a sort of a
context where you might
this is very similar to what i say about
the use of psychedelics or cannabis
you might set up a particular ritual
context perhaps maybe once a week
where you're listening to music while
doing mindfulness
et cetera but you don't want to do it in
general
because if you're listening to music
while you're meditating or discussing
those for
listening to guided meditation um you'll
indeed
you will in code that's called encoding
specificity
what that means is your brain stores not
only what you're trying to do but all
of the implicit context around it and
you will teach your brain
uh that mindfulness always comes with
japanese music
and then it will be hard to transfer
to your daily life this is a clear
instance of the principle of where we
can do things to make
the practice more intense in the
set but it actually undermines
the general project of affording
a very adapted transfer to as much of
our life as possible
and so this is an indication of how we
can be turning our
our set into something more a vacation
of a vacation and not enough of an
education
mark asked is it helpful to speak the
five promises out loud yes
it is i just do them silently because i
don't want to be imposing other the
people
but when you're by yourself uh saying
the five promises out loud
um is very conducive to uh getting that
intent
uh more deeply permeating through your
consciousness and cognition
and also um it becomes
something that we're this is a general
principle we're striving towards and
um i'll talk about this a lot um
especially when you get to the
neoplatonic part of the wisdom of
vibration
this is the idea of invocation
there's some things we just instantiate
what that means that's a philosophical
term sorry
what that means is there are properties
and processes uh
we we actually embody like for example
unquestionably
i am body digestion but i'm also
embodying
you know the unfolding of being in space
and time so the
the the number of things
aspects of reality that we embody not
just
think about um is actually quite
significant this is
a an idea about it's a way to bring back
the ancient
idea of sort of microcosm within
reflects important aspects of the
microcosm without
so we instantiate
a whole bunch of properties but we also
represent a lot of our properties
especially with language
and what we want to do is we want to
sort of like almost like stereoscopic
vision we want to move beyond
representing and just unconsciously
instantiating
into what is what we're invoking
we're invoking a process so when you
speak aloud
you're not just representing your intent
you're also instantiating it
it's like when you say i promise you're
not just representing your promise
you're actually making a promise you're
both representing and instantiating
and then you're reaching beyond that
you're trying to invoke aspirationally
like the very phenomena that you
are speaking and i know
some of you think this sounds creepily
like magic and we won't we don't want to
get involved with magic
but notice how when again you're making
a promise you're not only representing
something
you're actually instantiating it and
you're aspiring you're committing
yourself
uh to it into the future so speaking
aloud is a powerful way
to turn the promises into
invocations and implication is important
uh another question from our odd uh
jonas good to see your ad
again when i'm deep into the process i
can't resist noticing the darkness
behind my eyelids and being aware
of that enhances my meditative
experience i wonder if you can relate to
that and whether it's beneficial to do
that
it it depends what you mean by enhancing
your meditative experience
if it gets you into sort of a depth um
that a depth of awareness of your own
mind
this is again again not to keep
postponing
this is the issue again about what is
the role of the imagination
in all of this but what's the role of
the imagination specifically in here
what's the
role of perception right and so if
the perception and
sort and the imaginative engagement with
that inner darkness is something you
look through if it's like a lens that
you look through
in order to facilitate coming into a
deeper awareness for example
of the space between your thoughts or
the depths
of the psyche in the pasta then use it
if it becomes something that you're
looking at
then let it go and when you're looking
through it
you want to eventually make this less
and less focal and explicit
so that it becomes more and more about
what you're focusing on through the
image
rather than focusing on the image itself
it's it's this part of the principle of
inner coaching you want to get to the
point
where it stops being
it stops being like a method and it
starts to become a manner
of your consciousness and cognition um
admissif which i believe i believe is
ben welcome ben
uh observation thank you thank you ben
a constant reminder that
it's really important to share
observation and comments
it helps all of us observation my breath
seems to be getting increasingly subtle
as my concentration deepens that's a
very widely reported and normal part of
the practice
and it seems at the same time that
allowing my breath to become more subtle
deepens my concentration
exactly so what's probably happening
here
because remember one of the things we're
trying to co-activate and remember that
we're going to keep coming back to that
idea too
we're trying to co-activate both the
sympathetic nervous system
and the parasympathetic so we want sort
of
a high degree of activity
in one sense but we're also trying to
move into this deep rootedness
and the subtle breath is really really
powerful uh for really getting
uh the profundity um from the
parasympathetic
um activation how it can really
help to calm and open like open up that
space
uh so yes very much pleasure of doubt uh
brett
brad i know i owe you a couple of emails
i think at least one
um i i hope to get to those today
um can you elaborate in deeper past and
what it means to meditate on the space
between the thoughts
should we still be focusing on the
breath just on the brightness when
you're in deep vipassana
you move out of the breath as an
explicit focus
try to keep it like almost like a
background
of awareness it comes into
the mental as that sense like i said
that dynamic ground the energetic sense
so don't leave the body behind but
it's not your focal awareness and it's
coming into your awareness
insofar as you feel your awareness being
energized
a dynamic ground but that focal
awareness
is on the blankness the stillness the
non-thought
aspects of your consciousness so that's
exactly right
hey everyone thank you very much for
joining today i want to thank my techno
mage
and dear friend of marge amar and
my beloved son jason jason is sort of
apprenticing with ammar to
help increase um our redundancy for
managing
um all of the tech that's going on so i
thank jason for that
please subscribe to this channel to be
notified of the next video
um there's a good video coming out today
um
my discussion with uh uh jonathan pajot
um jonathan is brilliant he's the author
of the symbolic world
and every time he and i have a
discussion i think we get into some very
deep
but also very rich and juicy the logos
when you subscribe to the channel uh you
will
be as i said you'll become aware of
other dialogues like that on voices with
reiki
you'll have access to awakening from the
meeting crisis
which is the comprehensive lecture
series
um and you'll find these themes that
we're talking about in this course
link to other relevant themes and
situated in
a more encompassing uh framework of
philosophia the cultivation
the brotherly we're going to need a
better word that conveys the same thing
uh right but that the communitas love
of sophia maybe that works
please invite others who might benefit
by sharing this series
please brett is here and so are mark and
so is mark
uh please join the discord server to
chat with others
uh to do some of the movement practices
with others
to perhaps get into d logos with other
people
um and also to uh sit um
on the times when uh the sangha isn't uh
uh available to sit i mean this senga uh
um and i know that on the discord server
they're already independently
uh meditating twice a day a longer set
so have some very powerful resources
um there
please remember there's no live stream
on monday because it's a holiday
uh please join that discord server on
monday at that time
next wednesday i'll be teaching you the
arms
please if you haven't done it already
follow me on twitter for the latest
updates
amar and i are going to try and make
more use of twitter
uh to give out information about uh
saying that it'd be good if everybody
uh i know some of you are probably
opposed i tried it not to use twitter
for anything other than this kind of
thing
but this is probably the most powerful
way
we can get out news quickly if we need
to so
please consider doing that
please remember that continuity of
practice and the quality of your
practice
are more important than the sheer
quantity of practice
or trying to reach some uh punitive
perfectionist standard
there is no enemy worse than your own
mind and body
there's no friend no ally no true
companion on the path
better than your own mind and body be
lamps unto yourselves
and to each other i'll see you all next
tuesday
take good care everyone
you